howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show com that's Jim rut show com
this is another in our extra episodes
focused on the coronavirus 19 pandemic
our guest today is jordan hall a person
well known to many of our listeners has
been on the show twice before Jordan is
former corporate executive with various
interesting experiences he's one of the
most insightful and broad thinkers and
writers and talkers of our time and he's
a multi-dimensional troublemaker one of
my very good friends and one of the
people whose opinion I respect the most
I've asked Jordan to come on and we're
gonna talk broadly about complex systems
dynamics and the ability to respond to
crises like this but not only this
because this is not the only crisis our
civilizations gonna confront over the
next 20 or 30 years so with that Jordan
let's let's jump in why don't we start
by talking about the intelligence to
action our which we sometimes call sense
making if we you know one of the things
I notice about our current crisis is
there were intelligence reports floating
up as early as late December that there
was a chance of a seer of a pandemic you
know chances unknown but much higher
than 1% at that point it would have
seemed reasonable for the our
civilization our country to invest at
let's say 10 million dollars in doing
some early pre ramp for testing by
January there are much stronger signals
coming in from the intelligence field
and it would have been optimal to spend
50 million maybe to get real testing
ramped up put in some pre-orders for
ventilators
etc but none of that was done the
intelligence was never turned into cents
which was never bridged to action if we
were designing a complex dynamic system
to be able to respond to situations like
this how would we do it differently well
I think one of the things this actually
has been noticed in this particular
environment is a non-trivial fraction of
the people in the country were in fact
aware of the situation we're making
strong recommendations and we're
themselves making good choices so it's
actually kind of an interesting what
millon called like a sense making mono
cropping problem and I'm gonna you know
frankly point back to the notion of the
blue church as being a significant issue
so if you recall the basic structure of
the blue church is that you have a lot
of very centralized decision-making yes
you have sensors out to the edge you've
got intelligence agencies for example
that are watching what's going on and
they're kind of handing information
analysis up chain it gets handoff to say
epidemiologist and epidemiology can you
cut this large network of kind of
vertically oriented structures that are
trying to take information since make up
up up but to make choices there's kind
of a miss bottlenecks right certain
decision makers have to make choices and
oftentimes if an event occurs where the
is if the speed of the event right this
exponential growth rate is a real
problems what we're dealing with or the
complexity of the event the the set of
characteristics that make it difficult
to really even understand the nature of
what's happening maybe ones little bit
more detail on that in a moment or we
might call it like a subtlety like the
fact that there is a probabilistic this
fat tail characteristic that uh Nassim
Taleb talks about a lot those three
kinds of things just really really hard
for that kind of sense making a choice
making infrastructure to respond to well
I mean either has to over prepare
because it's just kind of designed to
move at that thickness or it has to
under prepare so what would be would be
potentially very nice would be to have a
mechanism where we have a substantially
more distributed capacity to make
choices and and where the sense-making
fabric is wired up to that in a number
of different levels so you could imagine
that if there was a way for her manage
of you if you could highly highly
distributed CDC kind of function and you
were getting some signals in the
environment that there was something to
be taken care of and like nine people
could decide we're gonna ramp up our
spending on this kind of medical supply
and you didn't actually have to ramp it
up to a large department head but a
small number of people could could
choose they had resources that make it
allocate to particular levels of
protection and then would end up
happening is as the signal became
stronger you would actually just see a
larger fraction of the overall portfolio
of choice makers making concerted
actions and in fact you can even see
them build into larger you know larger
collections of choices and so what would
then occur is that if the event actually
hit you would have a a reasonably well
designed response plan already in place
and then also because if you design the
system smoothly like the way the special
operations in the military work the
ability to then rapidly upgrade capacity
on the basis of things that have already
been prototyped but also be part of your
design that makes sense absolutely I
don't know and I'm gonna extend it a
little bit and you know let me let me
know if you think this is resident with
what you said suppose we had allocated a
billion dollars a year for these kinds
of adaptive responses so that right out
of the tax payers money through some
selection mechanism hopefully with a
fair amount of randomness and it had you
know ten thousand people involved in
making these decisions you know any
group of ten ten thousand people could
allocate some level of authority which
they had to invest right yeah for this
thing could have something like a crowd
funding mechanism so any one of these
ten thousand people could kick up a
crowdfunding site based on their reading
of the intelligence and say hmm I think
putting some money into getting ready
for testing in December of 2019 is smart
and ahead of the curve and oh by the way
my signing authority or my little pot of
ten people though I can get the cosign
with me our signing Authority is a
hundred grand so we're putting a hundred
grand on this and by the way we're
setting this notice out to the other ten
thousand that we have done this
and that's a signal which will cause
other people to look at the evidence and
either say hey these guys are ass clowns
and are worried about something that
doesn't matter
maybe I ought to think about this this
way we get a swarming adaptive gradual
and partial buildup of resources aimed
at these problems prior to the point
where you have to get a bureaucratic
person to make a decision yeah and
that's a that's a you know oh this is
all kinds of holes in that design but it
doesn't mean it's a bad direction I
think it's a good direction of what
would be a very functional design it's
it's actually interesting to notice that
one of my friends I gotta Adam Robinson
uses the signals in the financial
markets to help him get a sense of
what's going on in the world and that's
actually not that different you know so
for example if you if you take a look at
the stock prices you actually saw for
example the airline stocks particularly
International Airlines began to move
into a strong negative territory in
comparison to sort of broader markets
quite early into the into the event and
so the people who are in a position
where they have skin in the game and
have and therefore both interest and
motivation to have really sensitive
awareness and what's likely to happen in
the future
we're already discounting airline stocks
well and it looked like like early
January late December and I'm not
rooming Chinese airline stocks I mean
internationally non stocks and so if you
could imagine if there was a way he'll I
don't know exactly how to do if there's
a way for them to kind of like create a
long position which is basically what
you're saying in response mechanisms you
know in some sense like right now it's
funny like if you took a trading pair
and you compared like an airline stocks
to like telecommunications companies
like zoom conferencing you would see of
course that the zoom conferencing has
gone way up and every one cycle got way
down so you were kind of long a social
infrastructure that is responsive to the
environment now if you could what you're
basically saying is can we build a an
infrastructure that's more in the direct
hands-on that has a similar construct
you know a bunch of people reverse with
some form of skin in the game and have
some mechanism to you choose to make on
their own on their own on their own
account on their decision authority
certain qualities of investment on the
basis of what they think is unfolding
and then
has some mechanism where other people
can and again I'm sorry so yes you can
do that and then the next thing I just
wanted to bring up is this notion of how
do we say it right it's like chaos in
the trends in the transform from chaos
into order the very earliest stages are
the hardest right you just haven't got a
clue what's going on I'll give you an
example right now in hospitals and this
is not the case in China or Italy
because they've already been through it
so you know the details of what exactly
is going to go wrong in hospitals as the
as the case count starts to ramp the
answer is we don't know it's actually a
mystery it's fog of war and so the
learning curve on that front is
extremely high but once you've learned a
little bit if you have mechanisms in
place to scale those learnings across
the entire system you can very rapidly
respond right so if you actually wire
per system we've got highly distributed
capacities to allow people to use their
local sense making and the choices that
they make appropriately skin in the game
send signal out to the rest of the
environment and actually prepare the
actual infrastructure in a kind of a
heterogeneous way and then you've also
built a mechanism for being able to take
early prototypes and scale the learnings
of those prototype systems why quickly
then you have a responsive for structure
that can handle both rapid and complex
and subtle systems dynamics yes however
yes you can wait to learn from
experience but I would have suggest
another potential use of shall we call
it this anticipation fund is one could
do simulations I mean you know with live
bodies right for not a lot of money a
few million dollars you could test a
medium-sized County someplace and say
we're gonna literally overrun it with
bodies and simulate a pandemic and see
what breaks awesome it's funny if you
could just find a way to construct us an
environment where people were empowered
and incentivized to do that we're you
know making the wrong bet cause them to
feel some kind of negative consequence
we're making the right bag gave them an
asymmetric positive consequence then
yeah you could absolutely see some small
town going you know what we're gonna try
this and then those learnings would be
at least you know
evening for and in those early stages
meaningfully more than zero as a
significant differentiator yep that's
where I see this complex system dynamics
response unit they're the ones that are
gonna see it and they can basically
bribe people into it go to a you know
medium sized County and say hey guys
we'll pay you a three million dollar
bonus to participate in this we're gonna
spend another seven million dollars
raining up a bunch of people from
central castings that put ketchup all
over themselves and coming out of their
various orifices and we're gonna imagine
that you guys have a zombie apocalypse
callate grade pandemic here in your
County are you in right well sooner or
later he's gonna say yes so it's what's
interesting is you're saying that is
it's it is somewhat well-known across
the internet that there was in fact a
corona virus simulation that was done at
the level I think the World Health
Organization is some kind of
transnational organization not that long
ago like November I believe it was yeah
so you know the key is not necessarily
so if there's something about that but
the notion of doing that kind of an idea
exists and the challenge I think is to
figure out how to how to take the
learnings that have already been been
done by organizations like the military
I try to just to learn how to scale
those kinds of ideas into it into the
broader environment and what I mean
there's that around about the Vietnam
War we began to realize that we're not
fighting the Nazis anymore and that the
nature of the field of combat had a lot
more pace of change and flexibility and
and by the way variants of different
kinds of enemies you know getting into
fourth-generation warfare and asymmetric
warfare and so the the military just had
to learn to build a completely different
capacity to deal with something which in
the military domain is quite similar to
what we're talking about at the level of
just complex systems dynamics in general
because okay great
and then the next point is just to
recognize that I mean I guess in some
sense obviously now this is not esoteric
and we're spending I don't know exactly
what the bill on this thing is
gonna be but I know it's gonna be pretty
big and Julian's with the T right we're
talking yeah several T's so that's why
I'm saying you can afford to have a
slush fund of some considerable size
that as long as you can design it
fluidly and as you say was
in the game and feedback dynamics it
makes us shitload a sense to have a you
know system dynamics response team
spending serious money every year doing
war games developing capability making
bets sending signals etc to avoid
getting whacked for big T's right right
now we shouldn't know you know under how
I said this underestimated the the
challenge of actually building something
like this because of course you've got
to deal with the fact that it focuses
for example in the current circumstance
as I think you've tweeted there's a
series of decision points where a set of
interventions on the part of the of the
country radically reduced the impact but
the interventions have a cost and the
information environment is is subtle and
complex and so the ability to make a
choice to say ok I'm gonna make us a
bold intervention at X costs which
guarantees that I've actually made an
investment at this cost and and then do
not know for sure that you actually made
a wise investment runs into all kinds of
you know political complications so as
we're seeing right now how like
literally we've got a on the one hand
some cohort of people are saying look
shut everything down
quarantine everything do it for four
weeks and then was it called the hammer
of the dance I think that mayhem got out
that was really good the hammer and the
dance if you guys haven't read it look
it up typing hammer and the dance into
the Google and you'll see a damn
excellent essay and and so the dance
part is then okay let things open up and
then keep an eye on things with testing
and tracing all kinds of other protocols
and boom you can migrate this is like an
efficient frontier but of course that's
gonna cost something right that's gonna
have real impact on the economy and on
human beings it's not the you know
unaware of that so then you get the
other side and by the way the other side
is not batshit insane you know this this
Levitt guys his models are not even
vaguely unreasonable in his model say
it's actually not that big a deal we
just sort of sat around we you would
actually see that we would be a pop and
a fizzle and kind of be over and then
you would save all that energy
otherwise I put it in the economy and of
course there's a whole bunch of people
who don't want to have negative economic
consequences so you've got actually a
real significant challenge that in many
cases even as you can definitely do
stuff that's rising up from from sort of
distributed network there are points at
which choice making reaches levels we're
having a mechanism that can resolve that
level of tension is how do I say
decidedly non-trivial like exactly how
you that is tricky now of course the
answer to that is an answer that's gonna
be tricky for us to deal with which is
compartmentalization you know if I've
got the entire United States isn't
trained as a single object and the whole
thing has to make a single choices as a
chunk obviously what that means is that
we're putting more chips on that bet
whereas for example in the case of
Europe Italy makes one choice and Spain
makes another choice and and the
Netherlands makes another choice and two
to be sure particularly the case of a
pandemic there's contagion cross border
we should be aware of it but there at
least there's a decoupling so in
principle that should allow there to be
sort of heterogeneous choices and then
an ability to basically have a
resilience right you know you you've
mono crops instead of I mean you've
Polly cropper sort of mono crop there's
something to be we have to really think
about how we actually construct the
actual network or the geometry of our
choice making infrastructure so that we
can have the capacity make these kinds
of choices in a way that are don't
create very very heavy like all at once
big things that have to be made at the
top but can actually allow larger or
smaller pieces to actually make
effective choices that are in some cases
it may be weight weight differently that
make sense yeah and this is one things
is also coming clear to me is that we
should be as a society really thinking
carefully how to build our society in a
much more modular fashion right so that
you go down to the county level and the
county level has a level of resilience
to be able to stand in place for 60 days
right some extra warehouses etc if you
know in which case westchester county
when the new rochelle thing started just
said all right
boom westchester county is now on
lockdown westchester county by the way
is self-sufficient for sixty days no
one's going to suffer and we would have
probably nipped the New York
break in its bud but because the
Westchester County is kind of in a
confusing fashion interwoven with New
York City and everything else and that
there's no simple way to break the
circuits there was no simple decision to
be made right so no decision was made
till it was too late yeah and so this is
a I think we kind of pop up above and I
don't know if you mentioned this in this
call right we were chatting about before
if the message that certainly I have
been sending and I think you and I both
have been very much into the world and
large is this is this particular crisis
the the Cova 19 crisis and then the
financial crisis that is connected to it
is a example of just the normal this is
the world we're living in and it's a
world world war you were going to be
experiencing a very large number of
systemic perturbations that will have
characteristics of exponential
consequences and they'll have
characteristics of complex systems
consequences where for example a
response of the medical level actually
has implications in terms of like
unemployment lines and so we just have
to we actually have just have to
re-engineer the way that we do things as
a civilization to just be adaptive to
the environment that we find ourselves
in I mean that phrase should just be
obvious and then we just just look at
the realities okay what are the
environment we find ourselves in and
then you start making the moves so we
want to talk about like what's the
wherever possible end States like how
might this thing play out I can tell you
when one thing was extremely high level
of confidence like damn near certitude
is that it's not really a matter of if
we kind of we make these sorts of
changes it's a matter of when and how
painful so if you kind of take the exact
scenario that we're in which is if we
had just been paying attention better
and we just had built the capacity to
respond to the signals we were getting
and made choices better choices earlier
we could have saved ourselves an
enormous amount of pain and enormous
amount of money alright take that lesson
and apply that lesson broadly where this
event is the equivalent of you know the
first guys who are getting sick in in
China you can I can look at this event
and say oh wow this kind of thing is
going to begin to happen more and more
and more and the longer I wait and the
longer I stalled changing stuff but
need to change to be able to be
responsive to reality all that's
happening is that I'm delaying the
implications I'm going and raising the
stakes and eventually I will for sure
change because reality has a very strong
capacity to make me do what it wants so
the best choice is just to figure out
how to adapt to it now so you minimize
the negative consequences but you know
things are tough to sell on that yeah
but of course that requires people
moving from a linear essentially
Newtonian approach to the world to a
true complex systems approach which is
slowly propagating but it is by far not
the norm of how even very well educated
and experienced people operate yeah
that's for sure I mean it is there's a
problem of course is that it's a lot of
these things even if you hold those
kinds of ideas call it cognitively you
have them ideas if you haven't actually
experienced them in your life then it's
hard to do but I mean fortunately in
some sense everybody right now is
getting some sensitive like we're seeing
exponential curves everybody's producing
exponential curve you get into it we're
gonna watch the dots every day the dot
stays on the curve and like Wow look at
that that's what makes Mitchell curve
looks like and there it is and of course
by the way Ellen Musk's critique is sort
of beautifully accurate and completely
irrelevant which is that there are no
exponential curves in nature it's
definitely a sigmoid well by the way
there are things that are exponential
and then collapse those are also things
exist in nature but the first part of
the sigmoid treated as an exponential
because in terms of making choices
that's the way that you have to deal
with it Absalom and we do not want to
get into the top of the sigmoid here
fans let's be clear about that right
right so I think that's kind of the
moral lesson is to the extent possible
just recognize that the same--the of
1950s and there's lots of good reasons
to understand that the environment that
we are in many largely because of the
world that we built right this fact that
we have billions of people millions of
people moving every day through giant
global transportation networks it's a
big reason why this thing was able to
hit so hard and so fast and surprise to
many people you know the the fact that
we have increasingly networked our
electronics or the power systems into
cybernetic systems means that there will
be a cyber event
of this sort at some point in the future
you'll fill in the blank there's just
very large number of phenomena that are
part of the world that we live in that
have these kinds of characteristics and
so hopefully what will happen is that
the you know the pain and the learnings
the forced programs the unpleasant
learnings of this particular event will
lead to a choice to actually respond
with long term effectiveness to actually
say okay let's let's really do the hard
work of re-engineering systems that can
actually be adapted to this environment
that would be a really great thing
absolutely agree and that would be a big
positive learning to take help our
civilization headed a meaningfully more
intelligent way towards what comes next
because we are going to have a whole
bunch of these things between now and
the end of this of the century whether
it's the backlash from climate or
whether it's the hacker attack from hell
or whether it's it certainly will
include more and more of these pandemics
so we've got we've got to be ready to
deal with the world that's much more
complex than we're ready for today
because we're there let's hop back to
something we talked about a little bit
before this call which is how to start
to take action and prototype in this
area between sense makes making in
small-scale action taking and large
bureaucratic movements I think we talked
about you know the agile philosophy as a
way to start action prior to big
bureaucratic buy-in yeah so you know the
the military went through this
development and built up Special
Operations and then the software
industry went through the same basic
kind of learning curve and built up
agile I mean you know this there was the
the waterfall technique which works
really good when you're building moon
rockets but as the software industry
began to deal with the reality that the
landscape was changing rapidly and there
was great difficult to actually know
what what the end state was going to
look like they had to change the
development methodologies to use this
thing called agile which basically meant
that you you built something and then
you saw what happened then you build
more and then you saw what happens you
build more you kind of built an
iterative feedback but that included you
basically built a tighter
Suda Luke we know that language and we
can talk I mean I say I tend to go more
theoretical but you're talking about it
in terms of practicality and if you
think about the same basic mechanism of
the powering people to respond quickly
you can also think about your response
capacity could be using a lot of agile
methodology it's actually kind of
interesting to contemplate what that
would look like and how that would
empower people particularly now that
we're talking about things like ubi
going from insane and management that
crazy like you and I were like in like
10 years ago we're saying this needed to
happen universal basic income needed to
happen and I think we were pretty much
left out of the room and then Andrew
yang he's kind of left out of the room
three months ago and I think everybody
right now is only only dickering on how
much and how long and how to implement
it's quite remarkable yeah by the way
just just what I'm saying is that you
could actually imagine that imagine
universal basic income is in some sense
conceptualized as a standing reserve of
people's time focused on this kind of
like general purpose decentralized sense
making and choice making where you
actually could have makers people who
are making mechanical capacity could be
looking what's going on and say oh I'm
actually gonna spin up a project group
focus on being able to fabricate and 100
masks because as I'm seeing the data its
timing the n95 masks aren't actually a
very good idea and you know and you get
a tiny little micro fabrication facility
it's able to prototype something small
and but if it works then again you the
ability to scale ideas is actually very
easy
yep and having that communications link
to share I'll give an example our local
Staunton makerspace is already working
on prototypes for shields to go over
masks that they'll last longer it can be
3d printed somebody up in the DC area
designed it unfortunately they didn't
post the design publicly they sort of
require you to go and ask permission but
our people have and gotten the got in
the file hopefully this file will once
it's vetted will get out into the world
and maker spaces all over the world can
start building these things giving them
the hospitals that will triple or
quadruple the use for life of their of
the
masks mm-hmm yeah and you know it ends
up with a it's a very different topology
but you said something that thing's very
important is the communication channels
the the ability to have open comms so
that good ideas actually can be
perceived and flow not closed Tom's and
then give this ability for people to
identify good ideas and upregulate those
ideas and this is very much like Dave
snowden's point that's how you operate
in complexity is there's never an
endpoint you're always moving away
because the system is always changing
and your basic choice is you know more
of this and less of this your cost of
moving through an environment of up
regulating certain things and down
regulating certain things and you know
building an overall system at the
economic and at the sensing level that
has that kind of a characteristic to it
is is the story right that's the thing
we've got to figure out and it doesn't
look like this is the thing if it
doesn't we have to work like punctuated
equilibrium almost everything we're
building right now is a combination of
1950s and sort of 70s
Eirik Lujan's and then like this little
eruption that happened in software this
tried to figure out how to how to
operate in a non 1970s way but
nonetheless still doesn't fully operate
the way that it naturally knows how to
be yep had a very interesting
conversation on the podcast with Dan
mezack who's trying his damndest to put
agile into big corporations and here it
is 2020 and I was horrified how little
progress they're making right it's
happening but very very slowly as you
say most of the world it might as well
still be 1975 I imagine you've looked in
the government to be even worse yeah
well I happen to know the IRS is still
using what is it COBOL for running their
entire software system some sort of yeah
I think it is COBOL 1950s vintage
language absolutely well let's go to one
last topic before we wrap up here I mean
these extra podcasts are aimed to be
short and that is one of the things that
seems to be lacking in our national
response certainly lacking in our
national spots its coordination kind of
vertical and horizontal coordination and
as you know one of my pet mob
of the past it's on a smaller scale of
course is the Apollo mission control
system which was this astounding
real-time and non real-time series of
decision loops all linked together with
you know 1960 vintage technology but it
worked unbelievably well is it possible
to imagine building something like that
so that we could have a truly
coordinated operating on multi
timescales multi geographic scale ways
to respond to problems like this so that
we don't have you know one governor
doing X and the other governor doing Y
we don't have the president sending a
signal that's at 90 degrees from what
the head of NIH is saying so if we had a
is it possible to be able to have on
standby and activate on need a mission
control system for our whole society to
deal with one of these you know major
systemic risks yeah I think the answer
is yes I don't think it's trivial but I
think it's yes so let's just you know
try to make it somewhat concrete all
right so imagine this imagine and this
isn't by the way none of this is in some
sense hard so imagine if you had a
database that had everybody in it and it
had a mapping of kind of all of their
skills and maybe a certain kind of
psychological profiles like the way the
way they think and then you also had
some you know your the affirmations sort
of sense that that group is kind of
sensing things right so looking around
seeing stuff and there was a way to
escalate the sensing to the point you
could activate a much more intense
investigation it's kind of like you
think if you do a model like the way
that you actually know this is you build
this off for a model of but the way the
the human brain actually runs attention
right there's there's peripheral
attention we're for the paying attention
broadly and diffusely to lots and lots
of things and then there's a way for
there to be a phase transition we
actually get very focused attention what
was that right you hear a crack over
there and also the entire system
allocates resources to pay very focused
attention to that problem so imagine if
you had that right we could actually
have something with diffused attention
of our decentralized environment is or
into orienting orienting and then it
would a certain amount of energy is
pointed to something it pops and you can
then do you push a button and you know
the right expert the right people of
competence around the problem domain
swarm to the problem to maybe get like
thirty distinct working groups that are
all looking at it and all of their
outputs are kind of put into a general
location so you actually get this as a
Bayesian distribution of distinct
respect for these different working
groups and by the way I would imagine
actually problem probably want to
iterate that two or three times just to
say that you take the output of the
first process take all of that make that
the input of an iterative of the process
you have to do it's entirely new groups
where you scramble the groups you
actually have a really powerful model
for actually shifting cognitive bias and
groupthink and stuff like that but my
guess is that you could probably build
something like that that could do you
know two or three iterations and not
that long like a period of like a week
with 40 or 50 people and you could get
to like an 80th percentile of what our
collective and intelligence where our
capacities a population has to be able
to make sense of that event and at a
very high level like a radically higher
level than we're capable of right now
you know through all the important
questions that we don't know the answers
to if we want to ask if we have to kind
of expand this thing and so it'd be like
a phase transition from the diffuse
environment to a very concentrated
environment which could then have
another phase transition or or
de-escalation and the de-escalation
would be as far as we can tell rental
and now the red alert you heard the
crack you look over it's not a tiger
keep going or okay actually need to pay
more attention it uh or is it the
parasympathetic prepares to pathetic
nervous system which is it
I can always forget cuz the naming
always trigger yeah yeah get your knee
and their leg twitches that's your
parasympathetic nervous system with one
that triggers arousal this is why I keep
Daniel around well arousal would be deep
in the limbic brain now it's just one of
those two systems and I look over I
focused my attention and then I actually
get more pattern recognition at the
event that I'm looking at is a real
situation and then when I get is of
course at the biological level I get a
much higher level rasa link which
includes the activation of the limbic
system when I start seeing adrenaline I
have a higher respiratory rate and a
substantially large amount of
neurological resources are focused on
what the is that right so now that
the
rgeous system is now poised to really
orient its attention and now
increasingly as you say at that point if
my focused attention working group
started throwing out signals that this
is important then my distributed
actuation potential guys are going to
take a look at that and say oh better
pay attention now I've got my makers
working on building masks I've got you
know hospitals are starting to gear up
like that's a mechanism that can
actually have a nice feedback loop so I
think the answer is yes I don't think it
looks like Apollo but I think that we
can take a lot of the learnings of what
they did at an abstract level and then
say okay topologically how can we
actually replicate that using
contemporary tools to do something that
is well functionally equivalent to what
they did but is simultaneously able to
use the whole of the population is able
to operate as Lightspeed and is able to
do so in the context of an arbitrarily
large number of possible threat domains
and at an arbitrary scale and of course
arbitrary scale doesn't mean always the
largest because these things aren't
always going to be this big but there
will be other ugly things right if for
instance SARS was handled right that we
did bottle that up but there'll be
something between SARS and this so this
thing needs to be agile with respect to
its allocation of resources to be a bit
ahead of the curve never behind it but
no when did to absolutely deescalate
exactly I think we got a great design
very very high level functional
specification there get some whiteboards
it gets got damp down to it yeah well my
understanding is we've got four trillion
dollars to work on it and more so this
shouldn't be that hard to do you would
think just the that falls out of
people's pockets any final thoughts
Jordan on how people should be orienting
to all this well yeah I mean I think
that from my point of view we need to be
looking at this again from a complex
perspective so let's take a look at the
spillover effects I mean it's relatively
obvious right now that the financial and
economic implications are at least as
significant as the medical implications
and we also should be looking at the
mental health implications there's a
whole lot of different things that are
going on right now and being myopically
focused on the thing on the ground
because it's very salient and is you
know has a bit of a Hollywood moving
feel to it is unwise we actually do have
our vision much wider and taking a look
at the whole set of choices that are
being made and you
there's a lot of choices that are being
made they're going to have
extraordinarily significant lasting
implications and I don't really feel
particularly confident and the quality
of the folks who put in those choices
together just yet we the people may
actually have to start taking matters
into our own hands and presenting them
with what we think we're in fact the
right ideas yep that makes a lot of
sense it's time for we the people to
step forth
well thanks Jordan as always
unbelievably interesting I'm sure our
audience learned a lot and had some
serious stimulation all right production
services and audio editing by Jared
Jane's consulting music by Tom Muller at
modern space music com
[Music]